是, 大臣  第1季第7集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译:joinjoinjoin 校对:tpring 时间轴:i1984
任人唯亲
伯纳 大臣几点上电台录制节目
What time is the Ministerrecording this broadcast?
下午2点 汉弗莱爵士
Two p.m., Sir Humphrey.
你真的不能阻止他提及索里赫尔工程吗?
Can't you stop him referringto the Solihull project?
根本不可能      噢 天
There's not a hope.Oh, God.
他将把它描述成政府和私营企业
"It's a shining exampleof collaboration
成功合作的光辉典范
between governmentand industry".
他怎么能这么认为?   您告诉他的 汉弗莱爵士
How could he think that?You told him itwas.
一个耗资7千4百万 占地9英亩
Can a 74 millionbuilding project
地处市中心的工程 怎么捂的住?
in the middle of a city,be swept underthe carpet?
通过《官方保密法》
We'll use the Official SecretsA secret? .
这么大的工程 怎能保密
It's so huge
这是个大秘密 伯纳
It's a big secret, Bernard.
但您怎能用《官方保密法》
But you can't usethe Official Secrets Act
保护众所周知的事情?
with somethingeverybody knows about?
伯纳 《官方保密法》不是保护秘密的
The Official Secrets Act is notto protect secrets,
是保护官方的
but officials.
汉弗莱爵士 为什么您至今还不允许我
Why haven't you allowed meto show
把索里赫尔工程报告给大臣看 告诉他真相
the Solihull Report to theMinister, tell him the truth?
他还没问到
He hasn't asked.
既然他不想知道 为什么还要劳烦他?
Why bothera Ministerifhe doesn'twant to know?
但是如果他一无所知 又怎能问到呢?
But how could he askifhe doesn't know?
正是
Quite so.
汉弗莱爵士 我并不怀疑您的判断力 但是...
It's not that I'm questioningyourjudgement but...
但是什么?     为什么要这样做?
But?           But why?
伯纳 因为在索里赫尔工程报告里
Because, Bernard,the Solihull Report contained
有一段话质疑麦克·布莱利先生
a paragraph casting doubton the financial soundness
和斯洛安公司的财务稳健性
of Michael Bradleyand Sloane Enterprises Ltd.
其后看来的确具有洞察力
And the report's foresight had someinsight
和先见之明
in the light ofhindsight?
什么?
What?
它预见到布莱利的公司要破产?
If it said that Michael Bradleywas going to go bust?
拜托 伯纳 小心说话
Please, Bernard,watch your language.
关键是报告出来时 我...
The point is that, by the timethe Report came out, I was so...
或是说部门对布莱利坚信不移
orratherthe Departmentwas so committed to Bradley
愿意冒险将工程做完
that it seemed worth takingthe risk to see the project through.
如果大臣知道政府的合资伙伴濒临破产
If the Ministerknowsthis partnerwas going bust,
他就不会糊涂到在广播上宣扬 对吧?
he wouldn't makea broadcast about it.
伯纳 大臣们不必知道的东西还是不知道的好
Ministers should neverknowmore than they need to know.
这样他们就不可能告诉别人
Then they can't tell anyone.
像特工一样
Like secret agents.
他们可能会被俘获和逼供
They could be capturedand tortured.
你是指被恐怖分子?
By terrorists?
被BBC(英国广播公司) 伯纳
By the BBC, Bernard.
银行可能会扣下抵押品 这是个隐患
The bank doesn't knowwhetherornot to foreclose.
总之 我今天将和银行主席
I'll dine with Sir
戴斯蒙·格雷布克爵士吃饭
Desmond Glazebrook, theirChairman.
我们会一起做出点东西来
We might manageto cook something up.
为什么不直接下馆子?
Why don't you goto a restaurant?
总之 在这个时候不管怎样
Anyway, in the meantime,come what may,
必须阻止大臣在广播上提及索里赫尔工程
the Ministermust not referto the Solihull Project on the air.
汉弗莱爵士 这有点像是在掩盖是吗?
Sir Humphrey,this is a bit of a coverup, isn't it?
当然不是 伯纳
Certainly not.
这是基于国家利益的负责手段
It is responsible discretionexercised in the national interest
意在阻止正当程序
to prevent unnecessary disclosure
不必要的泄露
of eminently justifiable procedures
以免不合时宜的公开
in which untimely revelation couldseverely
严重挫伤公众信心
impairpublic confidence.
哦 我明白了 就像水门事件?
Oh, I see.It's like Watergate?
伯纳
Bernard!
如果你想改行当一名BBC记者
If you wish to leave the Serviceand become a BBC interviewer,
打个报告就行    抱歉 汉弗莱爵士 但是...
you have only to apply.I'm sorry, but...
这和水门事件到底有什么差别?
Howwas Watergatedifferent exactly?
水门事件发生在美国 伯纳
Watergate happenedin America, Bernard!
噢 是的 我明白了
Oh yes, yes. I see.
早上好 大臣      早上好 汉弗莱
Good morning, Minister.Good morning.
早上好 伯纳 抱歉我迟到了
Morning, Bernard.Sorry I'm late.
放到桌子上就行 乔治
Put them on the desk, George.
还有一小时 广播可不能迟到      没错 先生
I don'twant to be lateat Broadcasting House.
这个广播关于什么的? 北约 对吧?
What's the broadcast all about?NATO, wasn't it?
不 大臣 工业合作
No, partherships in industry.
我就知道差不多
Oh, yes. I knewitwas something like that.
还有谁在?     都写在这儿了 大臣
Who else is in it?        It's all in there.
照例是一个雇主和一个工会会员
An Employerand a Trades Unionist.
乔·摩根?
Joe Morgan?
索里赫尔工程的工会联合代表?
Wasn't he the TUC representativeon the Solihull project?
恩 大臣...
Er, Minister...
什么事 汉弗莱?
Yes, Humphrey?
大臣 你不会在广播上提索里赫尔工程吧?
You are not proposing to referto the Solihull project on the air?
当然会 这是政府和私有企业
Yes. It's a shining exampleof cooperation
成功合作的光辉典范
between the Governmentand industry.
是的 尽管如此 我更乐意您忽略它
But I would be much happierif itwere omitted.
为什么?
Why?
您不认为为时过早吗?
Don't you thinkit's ratherpremature?
怎么会 几个月前就动工了
Certainly not.Building started months ago.
确切地说 实际上是过时了
Exactly.Ratherout of date, in fact.
既过早又过时?
Premature and out of date?
恩 是不合时宜
Well, untimely.
您难道不认为公众会不感兴趣吗?
Would it be uninterestingto the general public?
会感兴趣 这是眼下进行的事
No. It's somethingthat's going on.
非常有趣   是的
Extremely interesting.Yes. Quite so.
太有趣了 其实风险在于
So interestingthat there is a danger
可能会淡化您的主要观点
that it might obscureyourmain point, perhaps.
我的主要观点是什么?
What is my main point?
伯纳 大臣的主要观点是什么?
Bernard, what's the Minister'smain point?
政府投资让私营工程
Private projects are more
更富于社会责任
sociallyresponsible with government money,
私人投资让政府工程
and government projects are more efficient
更有效率
with private investment.
看到没有?它强调了我的主要观点
You see?It underlines my main point.
你真让人扫兴 对吧汉弗莱
You really are a wet blanket.
总是泼人冷水
Just go about stirring up apathy.
大臣 我必须郑重建议
Minister, I must seriouslyadvise you
并诚挚请求您
with all the earnestnessat my command,
今天不要在广播上提及索里赫尔工程
not to referto the Solihull Projecton the air.
为什么?
Why?
什么?      我说为什么?
What?I said, why?
为什么?     为什么?
Why?Why?
是这样 大臣...
Well, Minister...
你不会是想把功劳归为己有吧?
Are you planning to takethe credit forthis yourself?
在下个月的欧洲政府行政会议上
At the European Conventionof Government administration.
什么?     你的主要讲话将很受重视
Yourspeech will makevery good reading.
但是 让我教你些常识 汉弗莱
Well, a fewfacts of life.
对人民负最终责任的是政治家
Politicians are responsibleultimately to the people,
功劳也属于政治家 而不是文官
and we get the credit.Not Civil Servants.
大臣 我很愿意把"功劳"让给您
I would be happyforyou to havethe "credit" forthis project.
但是我必须再三恳求您不要选择今天
But, I must beg, beseechand implore you not today.
不 没用的汉弗莱 我不会上当的
No, it's no good.I'm not going to fall for it.
我要从索里赫尔工程中捞取一切政治资本
I'm going to getall the political capital of this.
好东西我是不会看走眼的
I know a good thingwhen I see one.
请您听我说...   不 不 不
Please, do listen to...No. No. No.
大臣...   不行
Minister, p...No,
小汉
Humpy.
什么?   什么?
What?What?
要是我 我早脱身了
If it had been up to me,I'd help out like a shot.
没错 戴斯蒙
Quite so.
大臣看走眼 找骗子合伙
It's not the bank's faultif some idiot Minister
骗子卷款逃跑 这不是银行的责任
gets into bed with a kid,who runs with the money.
也不能全怪当时那个大臣
That Ministerwasn'tentirely to blame.
也有情有可原的地方
There were extenuatingcircumstances.
当初这个布莱利看起来很可靠
This Bradley chap lookedvery sound at the time.
没错 但换了你就不会上当吧
But you wouldn't have donea damn fool thing like that.
对吧?
Would you?
我是说 如果他当初只是周转不灵
When it looked like Bradleywanted a loan thatwas one thing.
现在只是他个人埋不了单而已
But nowhe can't pay his bills.
应该说 他似乎不能
Well, he is unlikely
兑现他对女王陛下作出的财政上的承诺
to fulfil financial undertakingsto Her Majesty's Government.
还是说他埋不了单嘛
Can't pay his bills, you mean.
要是船沉了 他很可能把政府的财政机构也拉下水
And Her Majesty's Government'sundertakings godown with him.
是的
Yes.
除非有一个信誉好的银行
Unless a reputable bank wereto take overthe contract
以参与工程为名接手布莱利的合约
from Bradley with a viewto participating in a project
表明政府决心
which Her Majesty's Government is
让工程成功获利
determined to make profitable.
没错
Quite so.
再敬女王政府一杯桑塞尔白葡萄酒
More Sancerrefor Her Majesty's Government?
像我说的 这取决于我的董事局
Well, like I say,it's up to my Board.
坦白说 可能行也可能不行
Could go eitherway,quite frankly.
可能行也可能不行   我明白
Could go eitherway.I see.
顺带地 换个话题 汉弗莱
Incidentally, to changethe subject completely,
你还记得你提过的
you rememberthe newMinistry Copartnership
新部门合作委员会吗?
Commission you mentioned?
没错
Indeed.
主席一职还没定吧?
The Chairmanshiphasn't been filled yet?
还没 戴斯蒙   因为要是...
Not yet, Desmond.Because if itwere to be...
应该有人会担任
should one be offered...
当然不是为钱 年薪是8000镑吧?
not forthe money,I mean, what's 8,000 a year?
160镑一周 还不是专职
160 a week. Part time.
对
Quite.
同时它也是个诱人的....
But itwould be a fascinating...
有什么定下来了吗? 内部的
Has anything been decided,informally?
我完全明白 要是你想要个公营机构的职位
You're looking aroundfora couple of quangos,
那我可以告诉你
and I can tell you,
私下说 你的名字在
in complete confidence,that yourname is
决选名单上
on the shortlist.
决选名单上?
On the shortlist?
公营机构怎可能突然间供不应求?
Quangos can't suddenlybe in short supply, can they?
电讯报今天有份报道
There's reportin today's Telegraph.
公营机构丛林:
"The Quango Jungle:
大臣们手头还有8000来个带薪官差
There are still around 8,000paid appointments
在公营机构中
within the gift of Ministersto Quasi Autonomous NGOs,
每年花掉5百万税收 肯定有两三个空缺
at five million pounds a year".You'll have two orthree spare.
他们是有不少空缺
There's certainlya lot of them around,
关键得找合适的人选
the point is findingone that is appropriate.
任命你得有依据
There has to be some reasonto appoint you.
牙科研究所咨询委员会怎么样?
What about the Advisory Committeeof Dental Establishments?
对牙齿有了解吗?   我是个银行家
Know anything about teeth?I'm a banker.
那也排除了牛奶销售局
And that rules outthe Milk Marketing Board, too.
对
Right.
那么海洋倾倒专家组代表
How about the Dumpingat Sea Representations Panel?
住在海边吗?   骑士桥大街
Do you live nearthe sea?Knightsbridge.
就在哈罗斯商场后面
Just behind Harrods.
不够近
Not nearenough.
这多少也排除了克莱德河净化委员会
That more or less rules out theClyde River Purification Board too.
臀肉牛排?   是给我的
Rump steak?That's forme.
肉品销售部 了解肉不?
Meat Marketing Board.Know anything about meat?
我吃它
I eat it.
不够
Not enough.
这也排除了肉类和牲畜委员会
It rules out the Meatand Liverstock Commission.
太平洋油鲽 先生?   海洋鱼类局?
Doversole. Sir?White Fish Authority?
马铃薯?
Potatoes?
马铃薯销售部?
Potato Marketing Board?
国家蔬菜研究所
The Governors of the NationalVegetable Research Station?
国家生物标准局
The National BiologicalStandards Board?
那是我的色拉吗? 谢谢 罗伯特
Is that my salad.Thank you, Robert.
农作物和饲料栽培委员会
The Arable Cropsand Forage Board?
食品和饮料培训委员会
The Food and DrinkTraining Board?
我要点法式芥末
Some French mustard, please?
哦 好主意 食品添加剂及污染物委员会怎么样?
What about the Food Additivesand Contaminants committee?
恐怕我对这些都不甚了解
I know very littleabout any of those.
老伙计 你到底懂什么?   没有
Well, what do you know about?Nothing.
什么都不知道 真的 我是个银行家
Nothing really.I'm a banker.
这不容易啊
This is not easy.
消防设施检查委员会
The Fire ServicesExaminations Board?
圣约翰救伤队?
St. John's Ambulance?
法式芥末 先生   谢谢
French mustard, sir.Thank you.
那么植物品种和种苗监察局
What about the Plant Varietiesand Seeds Tribunal?
见鬼 汉弗莱 我是个银行家
Dammit, Humphrey, I'm a banker.
谢谢
Thank you.
肯定有些弱势群体你可以代表的
There must be some minoritygroup that you can represent.
银行家?
Bankers.
你知道 公营机构最好找威尔士黑人
You see, the ideal quangoappointee is a black, Welsh,
残疾女工会会员
disabled woman Trade Unionist.
我们都在找这种人
We're all lookingaround forone of them.
你有没有碰巧认识的?   没有
You don't happen to know any?No.
那...
No. Well...
只剩下工业合作委员会
It all boils down to the IndustryCopartnership Commission.
我觉得这个职位还不错
I'd find that quite acceptable.
这倒是在我大臣的授权范围
Well, it is within the giftof my Minister.
你只需一个月露两次面
And you need only putin appearances twice a month.
没有太多的文件?
Lots of papers?
有 但没必要劳神去读
Yes, but itwouldn't be awfullynecessary to read them.
那我每月例会上就没什么可说的了
I wouldn't have anything to sayat the meetings.
太好了 你就是我们要找的人
Splendid. You're just the chapI'm looking for.
去广播大楼 谢谢
Broadcasting House, please.
抱歉让你久等了 乔治   没关系 先生
Sorry to keep you, George.
你送完我可不可以载伍列去趟下院?   好的
When you drop me, pleasetake Mr. Wooly on to the House.
伯纳 为什么汉弗莱想阻止我
Why Humphrey wants to stop me
在广播上提及索里赫尔工程?
mentioningthe Solihull Project on the air?
您不认为他给出了6或7个令人信服的理由吗?
Didn't you think he gave6 or 7 convincing reasons?
没有 你这样想?
No. Did you?
我认为汉弗莱爵士知道他在干什么
I think he knowswhat he's doing.
他当然知道
Sure he does.
我希望我也知道
I only wish I knewwhat he was doing.
我相信 如果汉弗莱爵士提了建议 那么大臣
I'm sure if Sir Humphreyadvises something, then,
无论建议了什么应该都是有建设性的
whateverhe does adviseis advisable.
那你有什么建议?   这可轮不到我建议
What do you advise?It's not forme to advise,
要是可以 我也只能建议
but I would advise youthat you would be
慎重考虑汉弗莱爵士的建议
well advised to followSir Humphrey's advice.
为什么?
Why?
是因为...
Well, it's just that...
某些工程有某些特殊情况
certain projects havecertain aspects which,
要谨慎处理 理智决断
with sensitive handling,given reasonable discretion,
当情况允许 也没有什么明显的理由
when events permit,there is no prima facie reason why,
妥善处理 如果一切顺利
with appropriate give and take,if if all goes well,
到一定时候 时机成熟 恩...
in the fullness of time,when the moment is ripe, er...
你在打岔 伯纳
You're blathering.
是的 大臣    为什么要打岔?
Yes, Minister.Why are you blathering?
这是我的职责 大臣
It's my job, Minister.
眼下在索里赫尔正有一个例子
An example of thisis going on up in Solihull now.
政府和私人投资
Government moneyand private investment
真正紧密结合
working togetherin a real partnership.
花言巧语
Claptrap.
我想这象征了政府的工作方式
And it's symbolic of the waythis Government is working.
我个人很关注索里赫尔工程 因为...
I've taken a personal interestin the Solihull Project because...
空谈   不是空谈 一砖一石都在那里
Not justwords, it is actually therein bricks and mortar.
如我说的 有实例为证
A concrete example,if I may put it like that,
我们的纲领在发挥实效
of the fact that ourprinciplesreally work.
谢谢 大臣 最后一句了 康威先生
Thank you, Minister.One lastword, Mr. Conway?
我重申 要贯彻合作原则
There's nothing wrongwith the principle of partnership...
首先 首先国家或劳工方不应
Providedthat there's no interference
干涉管理层的决策
in management decisionsfrom the State orthe workforce.
谢谢 康威先生 乔·摩根先生?
Thank you, Mr. Conway.Joe Morgan?
天啊 天啊 天啊
Dear, oh dear, oh dear.
我们都清楚康威先生
We all knowthat Mr. Conway is talking
在宣扬资本家的陈腔滥调
out of date capitalist claptrap.
合作的意义 只在于
If partnership is to meananything, it must mean
工会 政府和业界彼此平等
an equal partnership betweenunions, government and industry.
顺序不能颠倒   最后一句 大臣
In that order.Afinal word, Minister?
没必要针对我们   请各位安静
There's no need to be offensive.Gentlemen, please.
我想我们已经达成共识
We're all in agreement.
基本上已经体现出 只要我们齐心协力
We've shownthat if we can work together
就能打造一个新大不列颠
we can forge a new Britain.
今天很高兴能和两位重要打手...
And it's a pleasure to talkto two of the principal forgers...
不 重要嘉宾谈话
principal participants.
谢谢
Thank you.
尊敬的行政大臣詹姆斯·哈克
James Hacker, MinisterforAdministrative Affairs,
对话国家建筑协会
was talking with George Conway,
主席乔治·康威
from the Construction Federation,
和工商行政工会
and Joe Morgan, from the Commercial
常任秘书 乔·摩根
and Administrative Workers Union.
棒极了 谢谢各位 吉恩带大家去休息室
Splendid. Thank you all.Jean will take you to Hospitality.
真的不错吗?     一流的
Was it really all right?First class.
非常有趣 大臣
Most interesting, Minister.
哈克的废话能否剪到两个半小时?
Can we edit that awful Hackerwaffle down to two and a half?
别剪索里赫尔工程那些
Leave the Solihull bit.
乔 回见     好的 乔治
Joe, see you later.Yes, George.
冒昧提醒您
I hope you won't mindmy mentioning it,
哈克先生 您能否为我工会
Mr. Harker, but couldyou put a word in
伯明翰成员的特殊津贴表个态
formy members' claim fora special Birmingham allowance?
我不想在BBC录音室
I don't think I can conduct TradeUnion
里跟工会谈判
negotiations in a BBC studio.
而且 这归就业部门管
And that's a matterforthe Employment...
我知道 但你的一句话     不 对不起
But a word from you...No, I'm sorry.
我们已经有曼彻斯特津贴 普利茅斯津贴
We'd have a Manchesterallowance,Plymouth allowance,
萨德伯利津贴
Chipping Sodbury allowance...
这次广播之后 人们可能问及索里赫尔工程
Afterthis broadcast people mightask about the Solihull project,
想多了解一下
wanting to knowmore about it.
希望如此
I hope they do.
但据我所知 有些东西不该让人了解
But as we know, there aresome things betternot found out.
大家心照不宣就好
I'm sure we understandone another.
是吗?
Do we?
眼里进东西啦?
Something in youreye?
是希望之光啊     什么?
Just a gleam.           What?
哦 少来了 哈克
Oh, come off it, Hacker.
我们已经抓住你的小辫子了
We've got youby the short and curlies.
我开价低于伦敦10%的津贴
And I'm asking10 % below London allowance,
你杀到30%
and we'll settle for 30 % below.
对外宣传你大获全胜
Give you the creditforbeating us down.
抱歉我不发伯明翰津贴 别抱希望了
No allowance. You'd betterresign youself to that.
没希望的可不是我
I'm not the onewho will have to resign.
你在说什么?     当然是索里赫尔工程
What are you talking about?The Solihull Project.
我都不敢相信你在广播上把它往自己身上揽
I could hardly believeyou took all the credit for it.
勇气可嘉 但你中了什么邪?
Great courage, of course,but whateverpossessed you?
"枪林弹雨 左右夹攻"
"Cannons to the right ofhim,Cannons to the left ofhim,
"哈克先生视死如归"
Into the Valley of deathrode Mr. Hacker".
怎么样 先生?
How did it go, sir?
哦 很好 很好
Oh, very well. Very well.
我在讨论政府和企业界的合作
I was talking about governmentindustry cooperation.
中部地区有一个很有趣的工程
There's a very interesting projectin the Midlands.
我想你没听过 但是很有意思
I don't suppose you'd have heardabout it, but it's very interesting
如果你知道内情的话
if you know the background.
你不是指索里赫尔工程吧 先生?
You don't meanthe Solihull Project, sir?
是的 你听过?
Yes. You have heard about it.
你笑什么?   没什么 先生
What are you laughing about?Nothing, sir.
你听到什么?   真的没什么 先生
What have you heard?Nothing really, sir.
我们把它看作是政府和私人企业
It's a shining exampleof collaboration
成功合作的光辉典范
between governmentand industry.
有什么好笑的?你都知道些什么?
What do you know about all this?
行政部和布莱利先生办公室间的37趟车程
37 journeys between the Ministryand Mr. Michael Bradley's office,
从法灵顿街44号到索里赫尔伯明翰路129号
44 Farringdon Street, and129 Birmingham Road, Solihull.
37趟车程?和谁?
37 journeys? Who with?
前任大臣 先生 多数还有汉弗莱爵士
Yourpredecessor, sir,and Sir Humphrey, mostly.
开始几趟他们兴致很高
Very cheerful they were,on the first few trips.
不断说着合作
They kept talking aboutshining examples
光辉典范之类
of successful collaborationand such like.
接下来就开始愁云惨淡了 您明白吧?
Then the gloom startedto come down.
愁云惨淡?   嗯 不是愁云惨淡
Gloom?          Well, no not gloom.
更象是绝望 真的
More like desperation, really.
绝望? 为什么?
Desperation?What about?
您不是了解内情嘛 先生
You know the background, sir.
是 是的 没错
Well, yes, yes...
具体哪部分内情?
Any bit of the backgroundyou were thinking of?
没有 我是说有的事有些蹊跷时
No. When something's fishy,
它只是蹊跷而已 不是吗?
it's just fishy, isn't it?
你也不知道具体哪里不对头
You don't knowwhich bitthe smell's coming from.
蹊跷?     恩 我其实也不清楚
Fishy?         Well, I don't really know.
我只知道布莱利先生可能人品不错
Forall I know,Mr. Bradley may be quite kosher,
尽管汉弗莱爵士不同意
despite everythingSir Humphrey said about him.
这些您比我更了解 先生
You knowmore about all thatthan I do.
我不过是个司机
I'm just the driver.
对 对
Quite. Quite.
我不过是个大臣
I'm just the Minister.
是 我同意伯明翰津贴决不能发
An allowance for Morgan's unionis out of the question.
广播怎么样 大臣?
But howwas the broadcast?
我认为还可以吧
Well, all right, I think.
您认为?
You think?
我为索里赫尔工程大唱赞歌
I talkedabout the Solihull Project.
现在又不放心
And then I had second thoughts.
有什么特别的原因吗?
Any particularreason?
不 汉弗莱 索里赫尔工程还顺利吗?
No... Humphrey, is everything allright about the Solihull Project?
是的 大臣
Yes, Minister.
我知道施工进展令人满意
The building worksproceed satisfactorily.
不 不 不 我不是指这个
No, no, no,that's not what I meant.
眼下有什么情况吗?     眼下在施工啊 大臣
Is something going on?          Building is going on.
不 不 汉弗莱
No, no, Humphrey.
出了些事情对吧?
Something's up, isn't it?
对 确实是 大臣     什么?
Yes indeed, Minister.         What?
第一层楼出来了 第二层差不多了
The 1st floor is up,and the 2nd flooralmost up.
我指的是工程的基础
I'm talking about the whole basisof the thing.
哦 我明白了
Oh, I see.
基础你知道什么?     据我所知
What can you tell me about?As I understand it...
地基是6英尺顶极碎石
The basis is an aggregateof gravel and cement on
覆盖沙砾和混凝土
six feet ofbest builders rubble.
汉弗莱 你知道我是说财务方面
You know I am talkingabout the finance.
哦 您问我们和建筑公司签的合同?   是吗?
Ourcontractwith the constructioncompany you mean?
是 我知道工程款还在分期支付
The stage payments arein accordance with all the usual...
汉弗莱 我到底不知道什么?
Humphrey!What is it that I don't know?
您具体指什么?   我不知道
What precisely do you mean?I don't know.
问题就在于我不知道
That's just it, I don't know
我不知道 因为我不知道该问什么
because I can't findwhat questions to ask you,
我不知道该问什么 因为我不知道
and I don't knowwhat to ask youbecause I don't know.
到底什么我不知道?
What is it that I don't know?
大臣 我不知道你不知道什么
Minister, I don't knowwhat you don't know.
可能是任何事
It could be almost anything.
你有事瞒着我 对吧?   是的
Your're keeping something from me.Yes indeed.
本部门有责任保护大臣
It is the Department's dutyto protect the Minister
免受日复一日冲击部门的
from the great tideof irrelevant information
大量无关信息干扰
that beats against the wallsof this Department.
汉弗莱 关于索里赫尔工程的事
There is somethingabout the Solihull Project
我知道我不知道 我知道你知道
that I know I don't knowand I know you know.
我知道伯纳知道 乔·摩根知道
I know Bernard knows.Joe Morgan knows.
我的司机都比我知道
My own driverknowsmore than I do.
只有我这个
Only poorJoe Soap
面向全国的公开发言人
who hasto tell the public about it
还完全蒙在鼓里
hasn't got a clueas to what's going on.
汉弗莱 能回答我一个简单的问题吗?
Will you answera simple question?
当然 大臣 是什么?
Certainly, Minister.What is it?
我不知道
I don't know!
如果你告诉我 我就会懂得问
If you tell me, I'll ask it!
恩
Well...
什么事 弗兰克?     我们的会议
Yes, Frank?          Ourmeeting.
关于我的公营机构报告     哦 对 进来
About my quango paper.         Come on in.
读过弗兰克的报告吗?     是的 大臣
You've read Frank's paper?Yes indeed, Minister.
你对消除部门权利寻租怎么看?
What did you think about endingthe ministerial patronage?
几千个职位 任人唯亲
All those thousandsof jobs forthe boys.
很有独创性 富于想象力
Most original and imaginative.
你支持?
You liked it?
弗兰克 这两个词是汉弗莱最严厉的批评
Those are two of Humphrey'smost damning criticisms.
在政治上会大受好评
Itwould be a very popularpolitical move.
公营机构任命权上交议会专责委员会
Hand the quango appointmentsoverto Parliament.
任命贤才 而不让那些小集团和党棍送来送去
The best men forthe job insteadof old chums, partyhacks.
正是 应该为此立法
It should be legislated.
很新奇的提议     又是一个杀手锏
It is a novel proposal...That's the otherkiller.
但是鉴于现行体制运作平稳...
But when a systemis working smoothly...
平稳!看这个
Smoothly! Look at this!Proposal forChairman
最新公营机构 工业合作委员会主席人选
of the new IndustrialCoparthership Commission,
是戴斯蒙·格雷布克爵士 我问你
Sir Desmond Glazebrook,I ask you!
他从未在工业界干过 也没当过工会会员
He's neverbeen in industry,
还和本届政府唱反调
and he's said unpleasant thingsabout this government.
提名这种人 能叫平稳吗?
Is that a smoothlyoperating system?
他将是个出色的主席   他是个满口胡言的蠢材
He would be an excellent...He's a blithering idiot!
是 但也是个出色的主席   我很遗憾 汉弗莱
Yes, but an excellent Chairman.I'm sorry, Humphrey.
我有底线的 戴斯蒙·格雷布克不行
I am not going to appointSir Desmond Glazebrook.
大臣 非他不可   不 不 不...
Minister, you must.No, no, no...
拜托 大臣   不行 格雷布克没门
Please, Minister...No way. No Glazebrook.
除非我死了 好了?
Overmy dead body. Right?
大臣 在您最终决定之前
Minister, before you makeyourfinal decision
我想您该看这个
I think perhaps you oughtto see this.
索里赫尔工程报告
"Report on the Solihull Project".
为什么是绝密
Why is it top secret?
750万英镑...
"7.5 million pounds...
濒临破产
probably bankrupt proceedings...
工程倒塌迫在眉睫
inminent collapse of project"...well...
工程倒塌迫在眉睫!
Imminent collapse of project!
怎么不早告诉我?
Why didn't you tell me?
大臣 我深知您日理万机
I am conscious of the heavyburdens of youroffice.
但这会是所有报刊的头条新闻
But this'll beall overthe front pages.
会变成公共丑闻 灾难 真是...
It's a public scandal,a disaster. It's...
骇人听闻   等等 吉姆
It's appalling...           Jim.
这是选举前签的 算不到你头上
It is dated before the election.You're in the clear.
是的 但不幸的是
Yes, but unfortunatelyunderthe convention
根据大臣问责制 责任将归咎于...
of Ministerial responsability,the blame must fall...
大家都知道不是吉姆   没错
Everyone will know itwasn't Jim.Quite so.
民主责任原则要求
The principle of democraticaccountability requires
偶尔杀一儆百
the occasional human sacrifice.
当猎犬吠叫着要喝血...
When the packis baying forblood...
对吗 大臣?   他会指出日期
Isn't that right?He'll point to the dates...
哦 稍软弱的人可能会推脱
Oh, a lesserman might tryto wriggle out of it.
可是体面的办法只有一种
But there is onlyone honourable course open.
大臣已经明白了
As the Minister is well aware.
弗兰克说的或许有理?
Frank might have a point?
除非您今天没有公开以
Only today you have publiclyidentified yourself
工程接班人自居
with the success of the project.
那个广播!什么时候播?
The broadcast!When's it going out?
应该是现在
It's due fortransmissionabout now.
马上去BBC
Get on to the BBC at once.
停止   停止什么? 哦 对
Stop it!Stop what? Oh yes...
我祝您好运 但您该知道BBC的禀性
I wish you luck but you knowwhat the BBC are like.
这是个危机 是个丑闻
This is a crisis,this is a scandal...
如果你都这样说了 他们会
If you were to put it like that,they might...
会怎样?   放到黄金时段?
Might what?Move it to peak listening time.
怎么样?
Any luck?
索里赫尔正有个绝好的例子
Aperfect example of what can bedone is going on up in Solihull.
政府投资和私人投资紧密结合
Government money and privateinvestment in real partnership
我想这象征了政府的工作方式
to me, symbolic of everythingthis Government is working for.
我个人很关注索里赫尔工程
I've taken a great personalinterest in the Solihull project.
不是空谈 一砖一石都在那里
It's not just words, it's actuallythere in bricks and mortar...
象征着政府的工作目标
"Symbolic of everythingthis Government is working for".
汉弗莱 你怎能让我兜售这些东西
How could you let me sayall those things?
大臣 我只能提建议
Minister, I can only advise.
我提了建议 最强烈的建议
I did advise.I advised most strongly.
但是当建议者的建议不受重视
But when the adviser's adviceis unheeded...
好了 好了
All right, all right.
现在有什么建议
Advise me now.
当然 大臣
Certainly, Minister.
银行有可能接手
It is possible that the bankmay take over
布莱利和斯洛安公司的合约
the contract from Bradleyand Sloane Enterprises Ltd.
那就没事了
And all will be well.
银行!好的!对...   然而银行方面在犹豫
The bank! Fine! Well...The bank, however, is hesitant.
但碰巧他们的董事长
But it so happens thatthe Director in charge
将在明年退休 他正渴望
is to retire next yearand he's anxious
找另外的差事
to find anotherappointment...
例如公营机构主席职位
a chairmanship of a quango,for instance.
给他一个
Give him one!
就给那个
Give him that one you werereserving forthat idiot
蠢材格雷布克的职位
Sir Desmond Glazebrook.
谁是董事长?
Who is the Director?
戴斯蒙·格雷布克
Desmond Glazebrook.
他人不赖 真的
He's not a bad chap, really.
他总是公开抨击政府
He's always attackingthe government.
有时任命反对派也有好处
It does us good sometimesto appoint ouropponents.
以示民主 有政治家风范
It's democratic, statesmanlike.
我改主意了 这么任命很合适
Yes, that'sa very good appointment.
但你不能   闭嘴 弗兰克!
But you can't.Do shut up, Frank!
还有其他人知道这件事吗?
Anybody else know about this?
除了我们 银行 布莱利本人
Apart from ourselvesand the bank and Michael Bradley,
只有那个工会代表
the Union representative.
乔·摩根 当然
Joe Morgan!Of course.
这就是他那伯明翰津贴背后的玄机
That's whatwas behind his specialBirmingham allowance claim.
讹诈   没错 大臣
Blackmail.Quite so, Minister.
汉弗莱 我在想
Humphrey, I've been thinking.
要是格雷布克成了主席 他需要帮手吧?
Desmond Glazebrookwill need some support.
我想任命一个副主席
A Deputy Chairman,
一个搞过工业的人
someone with realexperience of Industry.
很好的想法 大臣
An excellent thought.
你有没有特别合适的人选供我参考
Is there anyone you couldadvise me would be appropriate?
比如说工会会员
ATrade Unionist, forexample?
乔·摩根怎样? 大臣
What about Joe Morgan,Minister?
乔·摩根!
Joe Morgan!
好主意 非常不错 汉弗莱
What an excellent idea.Well done.
公营机构要两个人才能运转 大臣
It takes two to quango, Minister.
马上联系他们
Get on to them both immediately.
我就是说这个 体制的问题所在
This is what's wrongwith the system!
任人唯亲 腐败交易
It's jobs forthe boys,quid pro quo corruption.
那我的公营机构裁减报告呢?
What about my quangoabolition paper?
很好 弗兰克 有独创性 有想象力
Very good, Frank.Original and imaginative.
新奇   新奇
Novel.          Novel.
我是认真的 你打算怎么办?
I'm serious about it.What are you going to do?
反正你不能把它封杀了
You're not going to suppress it.
我会呈给其他内阁成员 变成政党政策
I'll get it adopted as party policy.
要是交给媒体...
If the Press wereto get hold of this...
对 要是交给媒体
Yes, if the Presswere to get hold of this.
爆炸性新闻!   弗兰克 我一直在想
What a story!Frank, I've been wondering.
你想进公营机构吗?
Have you everthoughtof serving on a quango?
没门 你贿赂不了我的
You're not corrupting me.
不 不 当然不是
No, no, of course not.
但可能与其废除
But perhapsbetterthan abolishing
整个体制 倒不如改造它
the entire systemwould be to make itwork.
汉弗莱和我认为 应该建立一个
Humphrey and I were thinking,if we were to set up
特别委员会来调查并报告
a special commissionto investigate and report
全部公营机构的组织活动
on the compositionand activities of all quangos,
这可能是解决之道
that might be the answer.
解决之道!你一定得是...
The answer!
得有很高资历 擅长绩效评估
Itwould have to be very senior,mostly Privy Councillors.
但同时得有实际能力
But itwould need toosome very able people
研究过公营机构
who have studied quangos
深谙体系弊病所在
and knew the abusesof the system.
鉴于你的认识和关注
And in the lightof yourknowledge and concern,
汉弗莱提名你
Humphrey suggested yourname.
对吗?汉弗莱   埃瑟尔先生 对
Didn't you, Humphrey?Mr. Weisel, I said.
你改变不了我的立场
You're not going to changemy opinions.
做人要正直   当然
There is such a thing as integrity.Of course.
由于你的立场和正直
Youropinions and your integritywould make you
这个公营机构成员非你莫属
such a valuable memberof this quango.
提醒你 这是个苦差
Mind you,itwould be very hard work.
这个超级公营机构成员
Service to this SuperQuangowould involve you
需要常常远赴国外
in some very arduousforeign travel,
博采各国政府之长
to see how these mattersare managed
研究应对之道
in other importantgovernment centres.
日本 澳大利亚
Japan, Australia,
加利福尼亚
California,
西印度群岛
the West Indies...
塔希提岛(太平洋)   塔希提岛
Tahiti...            Tahiti.
是的 非常辛苦
Yes, thatwould be fairly arduous.
糟糕透了 糟糕之极
Dreadful. Dreadful.
但是这就是为人民服务 对吧?
But serving the public's whatit's all about, isn't it?
绝对正确   为人民服务
Absolutely...Serving the public.
为人民服务
Serving the public.
那我的公营机构报告怎么说?
And my quango paper?
无价之宝 你留着吧
Invaluable, take itwith you.
可以的话 我会拿一份复本存档
I'll keep a copy,if I may, on the files.
和索里赫尔工程一起
With the Solihull Report.
是 大臣
Yes, Minister.